Finding Aid for H. R. Crane Papers 1897-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
H. R. Crane Papers 1897-2000, 1933-1995
Crane, H. R. (Horace Richard), 1907-
1 oversize folders
2 linear feet
Physicist; professor of physics at the University of Michigan. Personal and biographical files include transcript of oral history interview with Crane regarding nuclear physics; writings, lectures, reprints, and essays, including biographical sketches of University of Michigan physicists; files pertaining to his involvement with the Midwestern Universities Research Association; and photographs.
0226 Aa 2; Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Professor Crane (donor no. 6005 ) and came to the library in 2000.
The collection is open for research.
Horace Richard (Dick) Crane was born in 1907 in Turlock, California, the son of Horace Stephen and Mary Alice (Roselle) Crane. He received his BS from California Institute of Technology in 1930 and his PhD in 1934. He came to the Physics Department of the University of Michigan in 1935 and spent his career there. He married Florence Rohmer LeBaron, December 30, 1934. She was an Ann Arbor City Council member (1957-61) and is now deceased. They were the parents of three children, Carol Ann, Janet and George Richard.
Crane's varied research interests have included nuclear physics, accelerator design, atomic structure, biophysics, radio-carbon dating, fundamental constants and geomagnetism. His most important work resulted in the measurement of the g-factor of the free electron and conception of the "racetrack" synchrotron -- a design still used in all major accelerators. He also researched topics related to physics teaching and science literacy.
During World War II, Crane helped to develop radar at MIT and the proximity fuze at the Carnegie Institution and the University of Michigan.
He was chairman of the University of Michigan Physics Department for seven years between 1965 and 1972. In 1972 he was appointed the George P. Williams Professor of Physics and was made emeritus in 1978. He was a member of Board of Governors of American Institute of Physics 1964-71, serving as its chairman 1971-75.
Crane played an important role as a founder of the Midwestern Universities Research Association (MURA), serving as vice-president 1956-57, and as president 1957-60. MURA was created in 1952 with the goal of designing a large accelerator laboratory. It was succeeded by the Universities Research Association in 1965 which designed and built Fermilab National Accelerator Laboratory in Batavia, Illinois.
Crane was elected president of the American Association of Physics Teachers in 1965 and received its Oersted Medal in 1977. For many years he edited a monthly column in The Physics Teacher entitled "How Things Work" (1983). One of the founders of the Ann Arbor Hands-On Museum, he built many of its first exhibits.
Crane received a National Medal of Science in 1986 for the first measurement of the magnetic moment and spin of free electrons and positrons. He is a fellow of the American Physical Society and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and a member of the National Academy of Sciences.
The papers of H. R. Crane consist of material relating to his career as a pioneer in the field of nuclear and accelerator physics at the University of Michigan. The collection demonstrates the wide breadth of his research interests which also include physics teaching, radiocarbon dating techniques, physics history and geomagnetism. The collection has been divided into four series: Personal, Photographs, Writings, Lectures, etc., and Midwestern Universities Research Association.
Subjects:
Crane, H. R. (Horace Richard), 1907-2007; Midwestern Universities Research Association.; Nuclear physics.; Physics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Crane, H. R. (Horace Richard), 1907-2007; American Institute of Physics.; Ford Nuclear Reactor.; Nuclear power plants--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Particle accelerator.; Physics--United States.; Phoenix Memorial Laboratory.; Scientific equipment.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal 1972-1996, 0.2 linear feet
  The Personal series includes a detailed bibliography of his published and unpublished work and transcripts of oral interviews with Crane conducted by other writers. Materials relating to prizes and honors he received include newspaper clippings, letters of congratulation from friends and colleagues, and event programs and citations.
  - Biography and bibliography 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - Prizes, honors 1968-1993 (Box 1)
    (also poster in oversize folder)
  - National Medal of Science 1986 (Box 1)
  - Appointment of H.R. Crane to George Palmer Williams University Professor of Physics Chair 1972 (Box 1)
  - Oral interview of H.R. Crane for a history of nuclear physics by R. Stewer and C. Atchley 1990-1991 (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1895-1995, 0.3 linear feet
  The Photographs series includes photographs of his experimental apparatus, including G-2 apparatus, the Michigan Million Volt Proton Accelerator, the Michigan Synchrotron, and the Michigan Reactor. Photographs depicting Crane participating in various professional and conference meetings will be found in the files relating to the American Institute of Physics Board, California Institute of Technology and the Michigan Summer Symposium.
  - American Institute of Physics Board 1964-1975 (Box 1)
  - California Institute of Technology 1930s (Box 1)
  - G-2 apparatus and equipment 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
  - General Scientific Interest circa 1963-1983 (Box 1)
  - Images from Publications (Box 1)
  - Michigan Million Volt Proton Accelerator, etc. circa 1938 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Summer Symposium 1928-1995 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Synchrotron undated (Box 1)
  - Michigan Reactor undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, including history of Michigan Physics 1895-1960s (Box 1)
  - Radiocarbon dating circa 1967-1972 (Box 1)
- Writings, Lectures, etc. 1933-2000, 1 linear feet
  The Writings, Lectures, etc. series contains evidence of the variety of research interests Crane pursued at various times in his career. Three files of reprints collect together Crane's published articles. Many of his research files contain topical correspondence. The file "G-factor of the electron, correspondence" contains exchanges with several influential physicists, including V.L. Telegdi (Apr. 6 and 18, 1989), L.N. Brillouin (Feb. 29, 1968); George Gamow (Nov. 9 and Sep. 24, 1967) and R.H. Dicke (July 1, Dec. 8 and Dec. 30, 1953). Another file pertains to Crane's service on a National Research Council committee to evaluate a government sponsored informational report on UFO's in the period 1968-71. In general, however, these files represent many of Crane's later projects and talks, which focused on physics teaching, the history of physics and profiles of his former colleagues.
  - American Physical Society Talk, "Nuclear Physics with No Money..." 1991 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Materials re: Samuel Goudsmit (1902-1978), Physicist and Donor of Egyptian Antiquities to Kelsey Museum 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - California Institute of Technology, Kellog Lab Talk 1981 (Box 1)
  - California Institute of Technology, Miscellaneous 1931-1995 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - History of Physics Department (U. of M.) including department centennial 1967-1995 (Box 1)
  - Fermilab talk on history of accelerators, repeated at U. of M. 1980 (Box 1)
  - G-factor of the electron article for Scientific American, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - G-factor of the electron, correspondence 1952-1990 (Box 1)
  - G-factor of the electron, progress reports 1959-1966 (Box 1)
  - Geomagnetism: notes for talks circa 1973 (Box 1)
  - Henry Russel Lecture: Research Club at University of Michigan 1967-1987 (Box 1)
  - Memoir of Arthur Rich (1937-1990) 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Memoir of David M. Dennison (1900-1976) for National Academy of Sciences 1968-1988 (Box 1)
  - Memoir of Donald Glaser, Nobel Laureate (1926- ) 1977 (Box 1)
  - Memoir of George Uhlenbeck (1900-1988) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Memoir of Harrison M. Randall (b.1870) 1997 (Box 1)
  - Memoir of Otto Laporte (1902-1971) for National Academy of Sciences (Box 1)
  - Obituary of Ralph A. Sawyer (1895-1978) 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Oersted Medal Talk for American Association of Physics Teachers 1977 (Box 1)
  - Pathological Physics 1979-1991 (Box 1)
  - Physics teaching: Ann Arbor Conferences on Curricula for Undergraduate Majors in Physics 1962 (Box 2)
  - Physics teaching: Guest editorial for Physics Today, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Physics teaching: Heat radiation to sky 1971-1983 (Box 2)
  - Physics teaching: Moon stereoscopes 1972-1985 (Box 2)
  - Physics teaching: Problems, raw material 1966-1981 (Box 2)
  - Physics teaching: Rattlebacks 1972-1992 (Box 2)
  - Radiocarbon dating correspondence 1951-1994 (Box 2)
  - Radiocarbon Dating Committee, Museum of Anthropology, University of Michigan 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Radiocarbon dating: CO2-CS2 Geiger counter 1960 (Box 2)
  - Reprints, H.R. Crane I 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Reprints, H.R. Crane II 1935-1949 (Box 2)
  - Reprints, H.R. Crane III 1950-2000 (Box 2)
  - UFO Panel: National Research Council 1968-1971 (Box 2)
- Midwestern Universities Research Association 1954-1994, 0.2 linear feet
  The Midwestern Universities Research Association series includes official documents relating to the organization (personnel, by-laws, organizational and liquidation documents) and also a file documenting the history of the organization including Crane's comments upon a published history of the organization and correspondence with individuals inquiring into MURA's history.
  - By-laws, descriptive, etc. 1954-1962 (Box 2)
  - History 1973-1994 (Box 2)
  - Liquidation 1964-1971 (Box 2)
  - Officers, personnel, etc. 1955-1962 (Box 2)